Mss.Rec.81 Mss.Rec.81
American Philosophical Society
Mandan-Hidatsa Ethnohistory and Linguistics
1969
Mss.Rec.81
American Philosophical Society
19.0 Reel(s)
Primarily consists of autobiographical stories, creation stories, and medicine stories collected by Alfred W. Bowers in earlier decades. The stories are read in segments in Bowers' English translation to two native consultants, who then translate the material into both Mandan and Hidatsa, or occasionally into either Mandan or Hidatsa alone. A small number of stories are told in Mandan only. Also includes English discussions of the Mandan and Hidatsa domestic life, material culture, personal reminscences, and histories of the Crow-Flies-High Band and the Fort Buford and Fort Berthold settlements. Bowers' original table of contents also available. Recorded at Fort Berthold Indian Reservation, North Dakota, in 1969.
19 sound tape reels (155 hr., 29 min.): analog, 1 7/8 ips, 4 track, mono; 7 in.
Bowers, Alfred W.
Scope and Contents note
A large portion of the recordings contain Crows Heart Autobiography (original tapes 18-38), which was collected by Alfred W. Bowers from Crows Heart, a Mandan, in 1947. The recording consists of the English version of the text being read in short chunks by Alfred W. Bowers, followed by free translations into Mandan, then Hidatsa, by Crows Heart's daughter, Annie Crows Heart Eagle, with the Mandan portion of the translations occasionally taken up by Mrs. Otter Sage.
The collection also contains an extensive number (tapes 40-54 and 58-67) of creation and medicine stories, translated as above from English into Mandan and Hidatsa, or into Mandan alone, by Mrs. Otter Sage, or Hidatsa alone, by Annie Crows Heart Eagle. This material includes stories about First Creator, Old Woman Who Never Dies, Corn Silk, Sikaraxa, stories of the origin of different bundles, and various autobiographical stories.
English-only conversations with Crows Heart Eagle and Otter Sage (original tapes 55-57) include discussions of Mandan and Hidatsa home life, household equipment, and material culture, as well as personal reminiscences about school life, the movement from old villages to allotments, memories of grandparents and their stories, and the history of various Christian denominations in the area. English-only conversations with Rufus Stevenson (original tapes 68-70) cover past villlage conflicts and the history of the Crow-Flies-High Band, the history of the Fort Buford settlement, and the return to Fort Berthold and adjustment to live under government control.
The 19 reels in the library's collection were copied by Alfred W. Bowers from his original reels, numbered 1-70. The library's reels do not contain original reels 1-17, which cover the beginning sections of "Crows Heart Autobiography." Tape 1, track 3; Tape 6, track 3; Tape 13, track 3; and Tape 19, tracks 2 and 3 of the library's tapes were unaccountably blank and therefore not transferred when the material was migrated to DAT format. Missing portions correspond to Tape 70, channels 1 and 3; Tape 60, channel 2; Tape 49; and Tape 54, tracks 2 and 3.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Alfred W. Bowers in 1971. This material was recorded with the assistance of a Phillips Fund grant.
Ethnohistory; Hidatsa Indians; Hidatsa language; Linguistics; Mandan Indians; Mandan language; Sound recordings
- Audio recordings
  - Question and answer interviews on history of village conflict and history of Crow Flies High Band [1 of 2], 1969; 01-01; 1.0 .mp3; 02:09:00; Bowers, Alfred W.; Stevenson, Rufus
    Scope and Contents note
    The Hidatsa language and people are identified as such in the recording's accompanying documentation, but on the recording itself they are sometimes referred to by one of its alternate names, "Gros Ventre." This Gros Ventre is not to be confused with the Atsina language of the same name.
    Existence and Location of Originals note
    This file is a compressed, digitized version of the original. The APS Library maintains the original format (Sound tape reel) as well as an uncompressed digitized version of this recording.
    Fort Berthold Indian Reservation (N.D.); Hidatsa Indians--History; Hidatsa Indians--Social life and customs; Indians of North America--North Dakota--History; Mandan Indians--History; Mandan Indians--Social life and customs
  - Question and answer interviews on history of village conflict and history of Crow Flies High Band [2 of 2], 1969; 01-02; 1.0 .mp3; 01:54:04; Bowers, Alfred W.; Stevenson, Rufus
  - Return to Fort Berthold and life of adjustment under Government control, 1969; 01-03; 1.0 .mp3; 01:58:03; Bowers, Alfred W.; Stevenson, Rufus
    Fort Berthold Indian Reservation (N.D.); Hidatsa Indians--Government relations; Hidatsa Indians--History; Indians of North America--North Dakota--History; Mandan Indians--History
  - Word list in Hidatsa, begins Study Culture Change, 1969; 02-01; 1.0 .mp3; 02:11:21; Bowers, Alfred W.; Eagle, Annie Crows Heart
  - Annie Narrative, Primitive Technology, 1969; 02-02; 1.0 .mp3; 02:13:31; Bowers, Alfred W.; Eagle, Annie Crows Heart
    Anthropological linguistics; Fort Berthold Indian Reservation (N.D.); Hidatsa Indians--History; Hidatsa Indians--Social life and customs; Indians of North America--North Dakota--History; Mandan Indians--History
  - Home Life, Food and its Preparation, 1969; 02-03; 1.0 .mp3; 02:06:53; Bowers, Alfred W.; Eagle, Annie Crows Heart
  - Household Equipment and Material Culture, 1969; 02-04; 1.0 .mp3; 02:12:31; Bowers, Alfred W.; Eagle, Annie Crows Heart
  - Movement from old village to allotments; School life, 1969; 03-01; 1.0 .mp3; 01:58:43; Bowers, Alfred W.; Eagle, Annie Crows Heart
    The Hidatsa language and people are identified as such in the recording's accompanying documentation, but on the recording itself they are sometimes referred to by one of its alternate names, "Gros Ventre." This Gros Ventre is not to be confused with the Arapahoan language of the same name.
  - School life, 1969; 03-02; 1.0 .mp3; 01:59:28; Bowers, Alfred W.; Eagle, Annie Crows Heart
  - Personalities of household and neighborhood; death of relatives; allotments, 1969; 03-03; 1.0 .mp3; 01:54:40; Bowers, Alfred W.; Eagle, Annie Crows Heart
  - Peyote and Christian ceremonies. Mrs. Otter Sage joins interview on spread of Christianity, 1969; 03-04; 1.0 .mp3; 01:59:13; Bowers, Alfred W.; Eagle, Annie Crows Heart; Otter Sage, Mrs.
  - Tells of grandparents leaving old village of Fishhook and taking up of allotments (Dawes Act); Scattercorn last days and beliefs, 1969; 04-01; 1.0 .mp3; 02:19:10; Bowers, Alfred W.; Otter Sage, Mrs.
    Fort Berthold Indian Reservation (N.D.); Hidatsa Indians--History--19th century; Hidatsa Indians--Social life and customs; Indians of North America--North Dakota--History; Mandan Indians--History--19th century; Mandan Indians--Social life and customs
  - Scattercorn (grandmother) dies. Tells some of grandmother stories to children. Details her funeral and property division, 1969; 04-02; 1.0 .mp3; 02:17:55; Bowers, Alfred W.; Otter Sage, Mrs.
  - Golden Valley Christians join community and break from Congregational Church. Father establishes own Church, 1969; 04-03; 1.0 .mp3; 02:19:40; Bowers, Alfred W.; Otter Sage, Mrs.
  - Puts into Mandan Old woman tales Mandan to parallel Annie C H Eagle's English-Hidatsa Narrative, 1969; 04-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:07:05; Bowers, Alfred W.; Otter Sage, Mrs.
    Anthropological linguistics; Fort Berthold Indian Reservation (N.D.); Hidatsa Indians--Folklore; Indians of North America--North Dakota--History; Mandan Indians--Folklore; Older women--Folklore
  - Continuation of discussion of local churches, 1969; 04-05; 1.0 .mp3; 01:51:44; Bowers, Alfred W.; Otter Sage, Mrs.
  - The Long Arm (Sun Dance character) Myth, 1969; 05-01; 1.0 .mp3; 01:56:41; Bowers, Alfred W.; Eagle, Annie Crows Heart
    This tape's contents given under the heading "Mythologies to cross-check for change in form and content since 1930."
    The Hidatsa language is identified as such in the recording's accompanying documentation, but on the recording itself it is referred to by one of its alternate names, "Gros Ventre." This Gros Ventre is not to be confused with the Arapahoan language of the same name.
    Anthropological linguistics; Fort Berthold Indian Reservation (N.D.); Hidatsa Indians--Folklore; Hidatsa language; Indians of North America--North Dakota--History; Sun-dance
  - The Long Arm (completed) Packs Antelope, 1969; 05-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:12:09; Bowers, Alfred W.; Eagle, Annie Crows Heart
  - Thunder Ceremonies [1 of 2], 1969; 05-03; 1.0 .mp3; 01:45:42; Bowers, Alfred W.; Eagle, Annie Crows Heart
    Anthropological linguistics; Fort Berthold Indian Reservation (N.D.); Hidatsa Indians--Folklore; Hidatsa Indians--Rites and ceremonies; Indians of North America--North Dakota--History; Mandan Indians--Folklore
  - Thunder Ceremonies [2 of 2], 1969; 05-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:15:27; Bowers, Alfred W.; Eagle, Annie Crows Heart
  - Hidatsa story about a brother and sister who got lost, 1969; 05-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:30:03; Bowers, Alfred W.; Eagle, Annie Crows Heart
    Anthropological linguistics; Fort Berthold Indian Reservation (N.D.); Hidatsa Indians--Folklore; Siblings--Folklore
  - Conversation about graves, 1969; 05-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:10:21; Bowers, Alfred W.; Eagle, Annie Crows Heart
    Cemeteries; Coffins; Fort Berthold Indian Reservation (N.D.); Hidatsa Indians--Social life and customs; Indians of North America--North Dakota--History; Mandan Indians--Social life and customs
  - Corn Silk Myth complex and Sikaraxa Myth complex [1 of 2], 1969; 05-07; 1.0 .mp3; 01:03:04; Bowers, Alfred W.; Eagle, Annie Crows Heart
    Anthropological linguistics; Fort Berthold Indian Reservation (N.D.); Hidatsa Indians--Folklore; Hidatsa women; Mandan Indians--Folklore
  - Corn Silk Myth complex and Sikaraxa Myth complex [2 of 2], 1969; 05-08; 1.0 .mp3; 00:20:41; Bowers, Alfred W.; Eagle, Annie Crows Heart
    Anthropological linguistics; Fort Berthold Indian Reservation (N.D.); Hidatsa Indians--Folklore; Hidatsa women; Mandan Indians--Folklore; Mandan women
  - Myths of Dog Den Butte; Shell Robe Ceremony, 1969; 05-09; 1.0 .mp3; 00:24:15; Bowers, Alfred W.; Eagle, Annie Crows Heart
    Anthropological linguistics; Fort Berthold Indian Reservation (N.D.); Hidatsa Indians--Folklore; Mandan Indians--Folklore
  - First Creator and Lone Man, 1969; 05-10; 1.0 .mp3; 00:16:02; Bowers, Alfred W.; Eagle, Annie Crows Heart
    Anthropological linguistics; Creation--Mythology; Fort Berthold Indian Reservation (N.D.); Hidatsa Indians--Folklore; Hidatsa mythology; Mandan mythology
  - Conversation about Mandan speakers, 1969; 05-11; 1.0 .mp3; 00:10:48; Bowers, Alfred W.; Eagle, Annie Crows Heart
    Fort Berthold Indian Reservation (N.D.); Indians of North America--North Dakota--History; Mandan Indians; Mandan language
  - Origin of Turtle Drums; Creek Ceremony Myths, 1969; 05-12; 1.0 .mp3; 00:26:29; Bowers, Alfred W.; Eagle, Annie Crows Heart
  - Two Incidents of First Creator, 1969; 05-13; 1.0 .mp3; 00:19:47; Bowers, Alfred W.; Eagle, Annie Crows Heart
  - Spring Boy and Lodge Boy, 1969; 05-14; 1.0 .mp3; 01:19:06; Bowers, Alfred W.; Eagle, Annie Crows Heart
  - Continue First Creator Sequence, 1969; 05-15; 1.0 .mp3; 00:47:31; Bowers, Alfred W.; Eagle, Annie Crows Heart
  - First Creator Sequence, 1969; 05-16; 1.0 .mp3; 00:34:24; Bowers, Alfred W.; Eagle, Annie Crows Heart
  - Conversations in Mandan and English, 1969; 05-17; 1.0 .mp3; 00:07:59; Bowers, Alfred W.; Eagle, Annie Crows Heart; Otter Sage, Mrs.
    Conversation; Fort Berthold Indian Reservation (N.D.); Mandan language
  - Turtle Goes to War, 1969; 05-18; 1.0 .mp3; 00:22:15; Bowers, Alfred W.; Eagle, Annie Crows Heart; Otter Sage, Mrs.
    Includes singing of the Turtle Song. The Hidatsa language is identified as such in the recording's accompanying documentation, but on the recording itself it is referred to by one of its alternate names, "Gros Ventre." This Gros Ventre is not to be confused with the Arapahoan language of the same name.
    Anthropological linguistics; Fort Berthold Indian Reservation (N.D.); Hidatsa Indians--Folklore; Hidatsa language; Mandan Indians--Folklore; Turtles--Folklore
  - Story about Coyote Chief and Some Children that He Had Met, 1969; 05-19; 1.0 .mp3; 00:44:02; Bowers, Alfred W.; Eagle, Annie Crows Heart; Otter Sage, Mrs.
    English and Mandan given by Mrs. Otter Sage. Hidatsa given by Annie Crows Heart Eagle.
    Hidatsa language is identified as such in the recording's accompanying documentation, but on the recording itself it is referred to by one of its alternate names, "Gros Ventre." This Gros Ventre is not to be confused with the Arapahoan language of the same name.
    Anthropological linguistics; Fort Berthold Indian Reservation (N.D.); Hidatsa Indians--Folklore; Indians of North America--North Dakota--History; Mandan Indians--Folklore
  - Moon's Marriage; Old Woman Never Dies Sequence continued, 1969; 05-20; 1.0 .mp3; 01:58:50; Bowers, Alfred W.; Eagle, Annie Crows Heart; Otter Sage, Mrs.
    The Hidatsa language is identified as such in the recording's accompanying documentation, but on the recording itself it is referred to by one of its alternate names, "Gros Ventre." This Gros Ventre is not to be confused with the Atsina language of the same name.
    Anthropological linguistics; Fort Berthold Indian Reservation (N.D.); Hidatsa language; Indians of North America--North Dakota--History; Mandan Indians--Folklore; Mandan language
  - Grandson and Bear, 1969; 05-21; 1.0 .mp3; 00:10:43; Bowers, Alfred W.; Eagle, Annie Crows Heart
  - Snakes of Red Butte, 1969; 05-22; 1.0 .mp3; 01:47:13; Bowers, Alfred W.; Eagle, Annie Crows Heart; Otter Sage, Mrs.
    Anthropological linguistics; Fort Berthold Indian Reservation (N.D.); Hidatsa Indians--Folklore; Mandan Indians--Folklore; Snakes--Folklore
  - The Snake, in Red Butte, 1969; 06-01; 1.0 .mp3; 01:25:09; Bowers, Alfred W.; Otter Sage, Mrs.
    Part of the Old Woman Who Never Dies complex of stories.
    Anthropological linguistics; Fort Berthold Indian Reservation (N.D.); Hidatsa Indians--Folklore; Mandan Indians--Folklore; Rattlesnakes; Snakes--Folklore
  - Old Woman Who Never Dies; Snake put in Missouri [1 of 2], 1969; 06-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:34:53; Bowers, Alfred W.; Otter Sage, Mrs.
    Version given on Related Recording by Otter Sage and Annie Crows Heart Eagle together is the same story despite alternate title.
    Anthropological linguistics; Fort Berthold Indian Reservation (N.D.); Hidatsa Indians--Folklore; Mandan Indians--Folklore; Older women--Folklore; Snakes--Folklore
  - Snake put in Missouri [2 of 2], 1969; 06-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:06:47; Bowers, Alfred W.; Otter Sage, Mrs.
  - Sikaraxa, 1969; 06-04; 1.0 .mp3; 01:49:38; Bowers, Alfred W.; Eagle, Annie Crows Heart; Otter Sage, Mrs.
    In Mandan only, by Otter Sage, with occasional remarks by Annie Crows Heart Eagle.
    Fort Berthold Indian Reservation (N.D.); Hidatsa Indians--Folklore; Hidatsa women; Mandan Indians--Folklore; Mandan women
  - Corn Silk and Corn Woman, 1969; 06-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:21:49; Bowers, Alfred W.; Eagle, Annie Crows Heart; Otter Sage, Mrs.
    First half in Mandan only, then given in English.
  - Second Corn Silk Story of Sequence, 1969; 06-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:23:05; Bowers, Alfred W.; Otter Sage, Mrs.
  - Corn Silk and Worm Face, 1969; 06-07; 1.0 .mp3; 00:25:02; Bowers, Alfred W.; Otter Sage, Mrs.
  - Corn Silk and Two Faces, 1969; 06-08; 1.0 .mp3; 00:49:53; Bowers, Alfred W.; Otter Sage, Mrs.
  - First Creator and the Children (last part), 1969; 07-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:15:21; Bowers, Alfred W.; Otter Sage, Mrs.
  - First Creator and his Mother-in-law, 1969; 07-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:09:48; Bowers, Alfred W.; Otter Sage, Mrs.
  - First Creator and Daughter, 1969; 07-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:11:40; Bowers, Alfred W.; Otter Sage, Mrs.
  - First Creator and Fat, 1969; 07-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:26:02; Bowers, Alfred W.; Otter Sage, Mrs.
  - First Creator and the Mountain Lion, 1969; 07-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:30:57; Bowers, Alfred W.; Otter Sage, Mrs.
  - First Creator's Exploits, 1969; 07-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:20:39; Bowers, Alfred W.; Otter Sage, Mrs.
  - First Creator Sequence, 1969; 07-07; 1.0 .mp3; 00:35:15; Bowers, Alfred W.; Otter Sage, Mrs.
    Consists of two stories, the first on a village of people with no mouths, and the second on First Creator and how the Raven became black.
  - Dogs that Talk, 1969; 07-08; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:20; Bowers, Alfred W.; Otter Sage, Mrs.
    Creation--Mythology; Fort Berthold Indian Reservation (N.D.); Hidatsa Indians--Folklore; Hidatsa mythology; Mandan language; Mandan mythology
  - Many Holy Women, 1969; 07-09; 1.0 .mp3; 00:06:48; Bowers, Alfred W.; Otter Sage, Mrs.
  - Ringworm, 1969; 07-10; 1.0 .mp3; 00:14:08; Bowers, Alfred W.; Otter Sage, Mrs.
    Anthropological linguistics; Fort Berthold Indian Reservation (N.D.); Hidatsa Indians--Folklore; Mandan Indians--Folklore; Ringworm
  - Pretty Girl, 1969; 07-11; 1.0 .mp3; 00:13:14; Bowers, Alfred W.; Otter Sage, Mrs.
  - The Hunters, 1969; 07-12; 1.0 .mp3; 00:44:27; Bowers, Alfred W.; Otter Sage, Mrs.
    Anthropological linguistics; Fort Berthold Indian Reservation (N.D.); Hidatsa Indians--Folklore; Hunters--Folklore; Mandan Indians--Folklore
  - Crow Flies High, 1969; 07-13; 1.0 .mp3; 00:17:26; Bowers, Alfred W.; Otter Sage, Mrs.
    Fort Berthold Indian Reservation (N.D.); Hidatsa Indians--History; Indians of North America--North Dakota--History; Mandan Indians--History; Mandan language
  - Conversation about Crow Flies High, 1969; 07-14; 1.0 .mp3; 00:14:20; Bowers, Alfred W.; Eagle, Annie Crows Heart; Otter Sage, Mrs.
    Fort Berthold Indian Reservation (N.D.); Hidatsa Indians--History; Hidatsa Indians--Social life and customs
  - First Creator and Robe, 1969; 07-15; 1.0 .mp3; 00:40:27; Bowers, Alfred W.; Otter Sage, Mrs.
  - Miscellaneous Stories, 1969; 07-16; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:20; Bowers, Alfred W.; Otter Sage, Mrs.
    Listed in table of contents as "Miscellaneous Stories" but contains only one story. Story concerns a woman and child, the child's transformation into a bird, and the woman's transformation into a butte.
    Fort Berthold Indian Reservation (N.D.); Hidatsa Indians--Folklore; Mandan Indians--Folklore; Mandan language; Mother and child--Folklore
  - Packs Antelope (First Part), 1969; 07-17; 1.0 .mp3; 00:38:16; Bowers, Alfred W.; Otter Sage, Mrs.
    Fort Berthold Indian Reservation (N.D.); Hidatsa Indians--Folklore; Mandan Indians--Folklore; Mandan language
  - Packs Antelope (finish), 1969; 07-18; 1.0 .mp3; 00:24:59; Bowers, Alfred W.; Otter Sage, Mrs.
    In two sections, first in English and Mandan, then in Mandan only.
  - Village of Only Women, 1969; 07-19; 1.0 .mp3; 00:33:55; Bowers, Alfred W.; Otter Sage, Mrs.
  - Conversation on Reservation life, 1969; 07-20; 1.0 .mp3; 00:12:08; Bowers, Alfred W.; Eagle, Annie Crows Heart; Otter Sage, Mrs.
    Fort Berthold Indian Reservation (N.D.); Hidatsa Indians; Hidatsa Indians--Economic conditions; Mandan Indians; Mandan Indians--Economic conditions
  - Two Men and Old Woman Never Dies; Myth of Snake in River Ceremony, 1969; 08-01; 1.0 .mp3; 01:29:48; Bowers, Alfred W.; Eagle, Annie Crows Heart; Otter Sage, Mrs.
    Identified as two stories in collector's documentation, though the stories blend into each other and there is no discernible break between the stories on the recording. Version given on Related Recording by Otter Sage is the same story despite alternate title.
    Anthropological linguistics; Fort Berthold Indian Reservation (N.D.); Hidatsa Indians--Folklore; Mandan Indians--Folklore; Older women--Folklore; Quests (Expeditions)--Folklore
  - Corn Silk and Sikaraxa, 1969; 08-02; 1.0 .mp3; 01:51:53; Bowers, Alfred W.; Eagle, Annie Crows Heart; Otter Sage, Mrs.
    Primarily in untranslated Mandan, given by Mrs. Otter Sage. Includes some informal commentary and conversation in Mandan with Annie Crows Heart Eagle.
    Anthropological linguistics; Fort Berthold Indian Reservation (N.D.); Hidatsa women; Indians of North America--North Dakota--History; Mandan Indians--Folklore; Mandan women
  - The First Creator Sequence, 1969; 08-03; 1.0 .mp3; 01:17:06; Bowers, Alfred W.; Eagle, Annie Crows Heart; Otter Sage, Mrs.
  - Dogs that Talk, 1969; 08-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:08:37; Bowers, Alfred W.; Eagle, Annie Crows Heart; Otter Sage, Mrs.
    English and Hidatsa given by Annie Crows Heart Eagle, Mandan given by Mrs. Otter Sage.
    Anthropological linguistics; Fort Berthold Indian Reservation (N.D.); Hidatsa Indians--Folklore; Hidatsa language; Mandan Indians--Folklore; Mandan language
  - Conversation of Grandson figure in Old Woman Never Dies stories and cultural loss study, 1969; 08-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:09:46; Bowers, Alfred W.; Eagle, Annie Crows Heart; Otter Sage, Mrs.
    The conversation includes discussion of the Grandson figure who appears in Old Woman Never Dies stories, the names of stars, the phenomenon of cultural loss in relation to Bowers' study, and changes in stories and ceremonial practices. The Hidatsa language is identified as such in the recording's accompanying documentation, but on the recording itself it is referred to by one of its alternate names, "Gros Ventre." This Gros Ventre is not to be confused with the Arapahoan language of the same name.
  - History of the Many Women (Holy Women), 1969; 08-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:14:38; Bowers, Alfred W.; Eagle, Annie Crows Heart; Otter Sage, Mrs.
  - Conversation on burial practices, 1969; 08-07; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:59; Bowers, Alfred W.; Eagle, Annie Crows Heart; Otter Sage, Mrs.
    Anthropological linguistics; Burial; Fort Berthold Indian Reservation (N.D.); Hidatsa Indians--Social life and customs; Mandan Indians--Social life and customs; Rivers--North Dakota
  - Hidatsa First Creator story, 1969; 08-08; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:27; Bowers, Alfred W.; Eagle, Annie Crows Heart
    Anthropological linguistics; Fort Berthold Indian Reservation (N.D.); Hidatsa Indians--Folklore; Hidatsa mythology; Mandan Indians--Folklore; Mandan mythology
  - Myth of the Ringworm, 1969; 08-09; 1.0 .mp3; 00:19:13; Bowers, Alfred W.; Eagle, Annie Crows Heart; Otter Sage, Mrs.
  - Myth of the Pretty Girl [1 of 2], 1969; 08-10; 1.0 .mp3; 00:11:05; Bowers, Alfred W.; Eagle, Annie Crows Heart; Otter Sage, Mrs.
  - Continuation of First Creator Sequence, 1969; 08-11; 1.0 .mp3; 00:18:04; Bowers, Alfred W.; Eagle, Annie Crows Heart
  - Myth of the Pretty Girl [2 of 2], 1969; 08-12; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:59; Bowers, Alfred W.; Eagle, Annie Crows Heart; Otter Sage, Mrs.
  - Myth of the Hunters; Myth of the Bear (First Part), 1969; 08-13; 1.0 .mp3; 00:43:16; Bowers, Alfred W.; Eagle, Annie Crows Heart
    Anthropological linguistics; Bears--Folklore; Fort Berthold Indian Reservation (N.D.); Hidatsa Indians--Folklore; Hunters--Folklore; Mandan Indians--Folklore
  - Conversation about digging sticks and house fires, 1969; 08-14; 1.0 .mp3; 00:20:15; Bowers, Alfred W.; Eagle, Annie Crows Heart
    Also discusses different types of structures, traditional pipes
    Fort Berthold Indian Reservation (N.D.); Hidatsa Indians--History; Hidatsa Indians--Material culture; Indians of North America--North Dakota--History; Mandan Indians--History; Mandan Indians--Material culture
  - Corn Silk and Toad Earrings Mythology [1 of 2], 1969; 09-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:20:20; Bowers, Alfred W.; Eagle, Annie Crows Heart; Otter Sage, Mrs.
    Anthropological linguistics; Fort Berthold Indian Reservation (N.D.); Hidatsa language; Hidatsa women; Mandan Indians--Folklore; Mandan women
  - Corn Silk and Toad Earrings Mythology [2 of 2], 1969; 09-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:29:22; Bowers, Alfred W.; Eagle, Annie Crows Heart; Otter Sage, Mrs.
  - Corn Silk and Worm Face Mythology, 1969; 09-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:31:39; Bowers, Alfred W.; Eagle, Annie Crows Heart; Otter Sage, Mrs.